A Guide to the Lyman Creighton Craig papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA134
Rockefeller Archive Center
Lyman Creighton Craig papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1935-1974
Rockefeller Archive Center
Craig, Lyman Creighton
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA134
32 Cubic Feet
67 boxes; 3 packages; 4 bound volumes.
Biographical/Historical note
Lyman Creighton Craig, 1906-1974, at The Rockefeller University (formerly RIMR) from 1933-1974, a chemist and biochemist. He was well known for structural studies with natural products and gained worldwide recognition for his development of the countercurrent distribution technique for the separation and identification of biologically significant compounds. The technique included the design of a stepwise extraction train which permitted up to 1,000 simultaneous quantitative extractions to be made which separated chemicals by small differences in their solubility. This countercurrent distribution process was used in separating, for the first time, the two protein chains in hemoglobin, an achievement which made possible a major structural study of hemoglobin, and subsequently, a sequence study of Bence-Jones proteins. This technique was crucial in the establishment of the structure of insulin, and in the isolation and study of hormones and other compounds and structures that are synthesized for therapeutic purposes. During World War II Dr. Craig worked on the chemistry of antimalarial drugs for the Office of Scientific Research and Development. In this study his laboratory monitored the purity of synthetic preparations from other laboratories and elucidated pathways of several antimalarial drugs. In 1963 he received the Albert Lasker award for his work on countercurrent distribution, which made significant contributions to basic research in diseases that are a major cause of death or disability. He also received the 1965 American Chemical Society Fisher award in analytical chemistry, the 1971 Kolthoff gold medal of the American Pharmaceutical Association and the 1972 Benedetti-Pichler award of the American Microchemical Society. He was actively involved in the Gordon Research Conferences as a trustee and on its scheduling committee and attended many conferences. Dr. Craig played an important role in University affairs.
Biographical note
1906 Born June 12, Palmyra, Iowa
1925-1927 Des Moines University, Des Moines, Iowa
1927-1928 Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa
1928 B.S. Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa
1931 Ph. D Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa
1931-1933 National Research Fellow, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md.
1933-1937 Assistant, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (RIMR), New York City, (chemical pharmacology with W.A. Jacobs)
1937-1945 Associate, RIMR
1945-1949 Associate Member, RIMR
1949- Member and Professor, RIMR (1954 title changed to Professor)
1973 D. Sc (Honorary) Northwestern University, Evanston, Ill.
1974 Died July 7 at his home in Glen Rock, New Jersey, Memorial service July 10 at First Presbyterian Church, Ridgewood, New Jersey
Awards
1963 Lasker award
1965 Fisher award
1971 Kolthoff gold medal
1972 Benedetti Pichler award
RU Committees: Advisory board of RU Mass Spectrometric Biotechnology Research Resource Spectroscopy committee., 1965 Chairman, Dean's committee for academic affairs, Faculty committee on program in organic chemistry and biochemistry: 1965 Chairman subcommittee in organic chemistry; 1969 Chairman, Committee of biomedical sciences research support grant, Committee to review policies and practices on faculty appointments and promotions, Faculty committee on biomedical sciences, Chemical sciences committee. Chairman, Faculty committee for planning of new building
Served
1953-1957 Editorial board Journal of Organic chemistry
1955-1969 National Research Council. Advisory board on Quartermaster Research and Development. Committee on Pioneering Research
1956-1963 Editorial board Biochemical Preparations
1957 Trustee, Gordon Research Conferences (GRC)
1962-1969 Selection and Scheduling committee GRC
1962 NIAD Allergen Standardization committee
1964-1967 Medicinal Chemistry Study section of National Institutes of Health (NIH)
1964-1971 Nominating committee for Lasker Awards
1971 jury to select winners of Lasker awards
1965-1972 Consultant, National Institute of Arthritis and Metabolic Diseases (NIAMD) (Artificial kidney and chronic uremia program of NIH)
1967-1968 Consultant, Commercial Solvents Corp.
1968-1970 Advisory board Analytical Chemistry
1970-1974 Board of Scientific consultants, Sloan Kettering Institute
1972-1974 Preclinical Psychopharmacology Research Review committee of National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)
1974 Jan Editorial advisory board Biochemistry
Member of National Academy of Sciences: 1963-1965 secretary of biochemistry section, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, American Association for the Advancement of Science, American Chemical Society (ACS): 1955 ACS program planning committee for NY section lecture series; 1960-1962 ACS award committee in chromatography and electrophoresis, American Association of Biological Chemists, Sigma Xi: 1964-1965 on nominating committee, Johns Hopkins Society of Scholars (Elected 1974 Apr), Harvey Society, American Institute of Chemists, New York Academy of Sciences (until 1958), New York State Society for Medical Research
Family Note: 1937 November 25: married Rachel Warner Parker, Children: Anna Craig Miller, Upper Montclair, N.J.; Mary Elizabeth Craig, New York City; David L. Craig, Montoursville, Pa., Brothers: Charles Craig of Palmyra, Iowa; David Craig deceased, Sister: Mary Bell Craig
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Lyman Creighton Craig were deposited with the Rockefeller University Archives on April 16, 1975 by Mrs. Rachel P. Craig.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 C844
Conditions Governing Access note
Access to this collection is restricted pending permission from Rockefeller University.
Arrangement
The Lyman Creighton Craig papers consist of thirteen series:
1. Biographical Material,
2. Professional Correspondence, 1950, 1952-1974,
3. Subject Files,
4. RU Administration,
5. Manuscript Materials, 1948-1976,
6. Conferences, Meetings, Seminars, 1952-1973,
7. Laboratory Data, 1945-1973,
8. Laboratory Data, undated,
9. Laboratory Notes, 1947-1970 and undated,
10. Instruction Manuals,
11. Accounting Records, 1970-1973,
12. Special Formats,
13. Collected Reprints
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: biographical material, correspondence, subject files, manuscript material, meeting notes, laboratory data and notes, manuals, financial records, reprints, photographs, slides, film, and negatives.
Medical sciences; Public health; Biology -- Research; Medical research; Hemoglobin; Insulin; Malaria; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Medicine, Preventive; Biochemistry; Chemistry; Blood
- Biographical material, 1
  Scope and Contents
  Includes bibliography; obituary material; personal correspondence; awards and assorted photographs.
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
    - Biographical articles (material supplied by L.C. Craig) (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes:.
      - Biographical sketch with some corrections, circa 1949
      - Biographical sketch with some corrections, RI News release, 1960 February 16
      - Biographical sketch for RI public relations office, circa 1964 March 2
      - Biographical sketch, Girlhaven, Inc., 1964 May 7
      - Biographical sketch, World Who's Who in Science (handwritten), 1966 February 8
      - Biographical sketches, circa 1966; 2 items
      - Autobiography for Second McGraw-Hill Modern Men of Science, 1967 January 12
      - Biographical sketch, Iowa State alumni assoc for possible distinguished achievements citation, 1968 January
      - Biographical sketch with some corrections, 1969 December 30
      - Biographical sketches from RU News; 1 slightly different text, 1970 March
      - Biographical sketch, circa 1971
      - Biographical sketches; handwritten translation from Italian copy for first European edition of Modern Men of Science, circa 1972 October
      - Biographical sketch, circa 1972
      - Oct Biographical sketch, RU News release, 1973
      - Who's Who in America 1 (1972-1973) 680, circa 1973
      - Curriculum vitae, 1974 February 15
      - Biographical sketch, 1974 February 26
      - Curriculum vitae, 1974 December 31
      - Lyman C. Craig, in memoriam. Presented at RU by Stanford Moore at 4th American peptide symposium, 1975 June 1
        Published in: Roderick, R. and Meienhofer, J., eds., Peptides: chemistry, structure and biology. Proceedings 4th American peptide symposium 1975. Ann Arbor Science Publication. pp. 5-16. Includes reprint.
      - News and Notes, v. 6, p. 6. On peptide symp, 1975 June
      - Lyman Creighton Craig June 12, 1906-July 7, 1974 in NAS biographical memoirs. 49 (1977) 49-77 by Stanford Moore, 1975 June 20
    - Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Bibliography supplied by Craig laboratory.
      Publications not listed in Craig bibliography.
    - Obituary material (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - RU announcement, 1974 July 8
      - RU News release, 1974 July 8
      - New York Times, 1974 July 9
      - Evening Tribune, San Diego, Calif, 1974 July 9
      - San Francisco Examiner, 1974 July 9
      - Newark Star-Ledger, 1974 July 9
      - The Record, Hackensack, NJ, 1974 July 9
      - Los Angeles Times, 1974 July 10
      - Washington Post, 1974 July 10
      - Detroit Free Press, 1974 July 10
      - Drug and Cosmetic Industry, 1974 August
      - Correspondence after L.C. Craig death
      - NIH to L.C. Craig. Re evaluation of P.T. Englund research career development award with Aug 29 reply, 1974 July 25
      - A.F. Hofmann to L.C. Craig with Aug 29 reply, 1974 July 25
      - K. Tsuji to L.C. Craig. Request for bacitracin sample with Sept 20 reply, 1974 September 10
    - Personal correspondence (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Arrangement note
      Arranged in chronological order.
      - Iowa State College to L.C. Craig. Exchange on L.C. Craig nomination for 1953 Chicago alumni merit, award, 1953 April 23-June
        Includes Craig biography (handwritten).
      - L.C. Craig to Allstate Insurance. On cost of car windows glass replacement, 1953 October 1
      - L.C. Craig to J.H. Hilton and D.F. Graves, 1958 June 3; 2 items
        Re Iowa State College centennial recognition and award day.
      - L.C. Craig to Mr. and Mrs. Claude E. Swain. On cancer treatment, 1965 March 1
      - W.A. Bayliss to L.C. Craig. Re Tony Campo retirement, 1970 March 12
      - L.C. Craig to A. Campo. On retirement, 1970 May 17
      - Announcement of E. Klenk death, 1972 January 3
      - L.C. Craig to Grete Klenk. Letter of condolence, 1972 January 7
      - Harvey Society to L.C. Craig. On election to life membership, 1972 April 18
      - L.C. Craig to Harvey Society. Acknowledgement of election to life membership, 1972 April 27
      - L. Kreider to L.C. Craig. Congratulations on 1972 Benedetti-Pichler award, 1972 August 19
      - L.C. Craig to L. Kreider. Acknowledgment of congratulations, 1972 September 14
      - C.P. Chase, M. Broadbent and B. Lehrer to L.C. Craig. On Ruth Mandelbaum retirement, 1973 September 24
      - L.C. Craig to R. Mandelbaum. About retirement, 1973 October 3
      - L.C. Craig to D. Mauzerall. Letter of appreciation when hospitalized, 1974 March 4
      - J.W. Parsons to L.C. Craig. About 50 years high school reunion (handwritten), 1974 April 7
      - L.C. Craig to J.W. Parsons. On probable inability to attend due to ill health, 1974 April 17
      - Correspondence deals with election to The Johns Hopkins Society of Scholars and Inability to attend, 1974 April 12-May 30
        Includes RU News release.
      - D. Lyons, M. Pedersen, C. Valli to L.C. Craig. On Pam and Roger Elliot retirement, 1974 May 8
      - L.C. Craig to Mr. and Mrs. Elliot. On retirement, circa 1974 May 8
    - Personal correspondence (family) (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - David Craig (brother)
        - L.C. Craig to D. Craig. About D. Craig visit, 1957 August 30
        - L.C. Craig to D. Craig. About D. Craig visit, 1958 April 2
        - L.C. Craig to D. Craig. About D. Craig attending GRC, 1958 May 2
        - D. Craig and N.M. Trivisonno reprint, circa 1963 February
        - L.C. Craig to D. Craig. About European visitors, 1963 April 26
        - H.L. Trumbell to L.C. Craig. On David Craig biographical article for Rubber Chemistry and Technology (handwritten), 1964 September 5
        - L.C. Craig to H.L. Trumbell. On D. Craig article, 1964 September 9
        - R.M. Pierson to L.C. Craig. About symposium honoring D. Craig (handwritten) on magazine announcement, 1968 June 4
        - L.C. Craig to R.M. Pierson. On symposium honoring D. Craig, 1968 June 10
      - Mary Bell Craig (sister)
        - L.C. Craig to Mary Bell. On flight, 1956 April 9
        - P.K. Hughes to D. Karnofsky. On Mary Bell treatment for cancer and L.C. Craig involvement (photocopy), 1965 January 22
        - D. Karnofsky to P.K. Hughes. On suggested treatment for Mary Bell, 1965 January 28; Photocopy
        - L.C. Craig to D. Karnofsky. Thank you for advice on treatment for sister, 1965 March 4
        - L.C. Craig to D. Karnofsky. On positive results of recommended treatment for sister, 1965 October 28
        - D. Karnofsky to L.C. Craig. Thank you for follow up on Mary Bell, 1965 November 8
    - Summaries of scientific work (undated); scientific laboratory personnel, 1945-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Summaries of scientific work of L.C. Craig while at RI (thru CCD)
        Includes final carbon copy, copy with corrections and handwritten copy.
      - "L.C. Craig biographical account with emphasis on CCD work", Typescript with corrections
      - "Membrane diffusion", Typescript
      - "Thin film dialysis including countercurrent dialysis", Typescript
      - Photocopy "Most significant scientific and scholarly accomplishments of the Craig laboratory"
      - Craig scientific laboratory personnel listing, 1945-1974
        Includes present address; some addresses unknown; with an asterisk* indicated for those working in general area of protein peptide chemistry.
    - Lasker award, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      In 1963 Albert Lasker award for basic medical research presented to L.C. Craig for CCD work.
      Correspondents include: Lewis L. Engel, Philip Handler, W. George Parks, Willard C. Rappleye, Howard Rasmussen, Lloyd E. Rozeboom, James A. Shannon, Elwood O. Titus, Arnold Weissberger.
      Also includes reprint of: "Citation", L.C. Craig "Acceptance of the Albert Lasker basic medical research award" and L.C. Craig award lecture "The isolation of active principles in pure form by partition" and award winner tag.
    - Coleman laboratory equipment award, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      1964 November 12 Dr. Craig recipient of a Coleman gold plated junior spectrophotometer from Coleman Instruments Corp who in search for oldest operating Junior A-003 spectrophotometer found one in use in Craig laboratory.
      Includes photocopy of Coleman Readout v. 1,no. 4 (1964) reporting search and award.
    - Fisher award in analytical chemistry (ACS), 1966 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Phoenix, Arizona ACS winter meeting L.C. Craig presented Fisher award in analytical chemistry for devising CCD.
      Symposium honoring L.C. Craig, he presents award address "The use of membrane diffusion as an analytical tool".
      Correspondence includes award announcements; Craig biographical sketch; awards, symposium and awards dinner programs; corrected copy and abstract of presentation; 22 letters of congratulations with Craig replies.
      Correspondents include: Nelson J. Leonard, Robert A. Harte, Sidney W. Fox, Walter Kauzman, Henry Gilman, Philip J. Elving, Howard Rasmussen, Karl Kammermeyer, Marshall Gates, Lewis L. Engel, Otto Isler.
      Also includes 1966 May 10 photocopy on Fisher award for publication in The Laboratory; recommendation for Charles Banks for 1968 Fisher award and undated galley proof with corrections on Craig Fisher award (Editor's note: NPI).
    - Kolthoff gold medal award, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      1971 March 27-April 2 San Francisco, Calif. American Pharmaceutical Association (APhA) Academy of Pharmaceutical Sciences meeting L.C. Craig receives Kolthoff gold medal award on 1971 Mar 31 and presents "The use of membranes for analysis and biochemical investigation of drugs".
      Correspondence includes award announcements and publicity material in apha newsletter, APhA news release and Academy Reporter; copy of presentation and letter of congratulations.
    - Photographs, undated, 1942?-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      L.C. Craig, others, laboratory interiors and equipment; nd, 1942 (?) -1972 Assorted personal photographs; scientists; friends; some identified and dated.
      - group photograph of participants of GRC on separation and purification (L.C. Craig chairman). 3 copies with participant identification, 1958 June 16-20
      - Swiss-American Foundation dinner honoring Prof Karrer, 1960 September 22
        3 photographs, 2 of which include L.C. Craig. Identified.
      - L.C. Craig receiving Coleman gold plated junior spectrophotometer, 1964 November 12
      - Group photograph of 1947-1972 recipients of ACS Fisher award at symposium. Identified
      - L.C. Craig explaining CCD apparatus on T.V. series. 4 copies, [Year?) May 19
      - L.C. Craig laboratory interiors and countercurrent distribution apparatus, 1959-1961
- Professional correspondence, 1950 1952-1974; 2
  Includes purchase of CCD apparatus from Mr. Otto Post; requests for chemical samples; requests for reprints; applications for staff appointments (alphabetical); correspondence with and about students (alphabetical); information on methodology and scientific techniques. [Except O.S.R.D. correspondence 1940-1946 in Box no. 19].
  Arranged in alphabetical order including incoming and outgoing letters. Number in parenthesis indicates number of items.
  - A
    - Abraham, E.P., 1952 November 18; 10 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes 1952 Nov. 18 Oxford, England University of Oxford lecture "The application of CCD to biochemical problems".
    - Academic Press, 1955-1956 1964; 10 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Acker, T.E. Curriculum vitae, 1 letter (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Adams, R.M., 1 letter (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Adams, Roger. Craig becomes member of CASE (Committee of the Arts and Sciences for Eisenhower), 2 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Adler, E., 5 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Advances in Analytical Chemistry and Instrumentation, 8 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Ms: About chapter "Differential dialysis" for. Published in 1965. Includes list of contributors and contract with publisher.
    - Ainsworth, C., 2 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Alders, L., 2 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Alderton, G., 2 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Ali, K.M. Curriculum vitae, 2 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Alms, H. Curriculum vitae, 1 letter (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Altschul, A.M., 2 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences. 1961 May 10 elected member, 4 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) (Box 2, Folder 1)
      [See under: Lectures 1962 Dec in box no].
    - American Cyanamid Co., 1 letter (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - American Association of University Professors, 2 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - American-Scandinavian Foundation, 1 letter (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Analytical Biochemistry. Mss reviews for publication in, 5 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Andrews, P., 3 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes Andrews "Estimation of molecular weights of proteins by gel filtration".
    - Anfinsen, C.B., 8 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Ansevin, A.T. At RU 1961-1964, 1961-1964 1970; 20 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes curriculum vitae.
    - Anson, M.L., 2 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics, 1954-1956 1960-1967; 15 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes reviews of mss for publication in...
    - Arcos, J.C., 2 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Arquilla, E.R., 2 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Atoms for Peace Awards, 8 letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Invitations to award ceremonies; booklets.
    - Agosta, Wm. C. RU Professor. Lab colleague; becomes full RU professor, 1966-1974; 65 letters (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Consists of recommendations for grants and promotion (biographical material and bibliography) and recommendations for Agosta graduate students: Includes ms 1967 Feb 28 "Transannular and interannular effects in 1,8- (l',8') - napthalylnapthalene and related compounds".
    - Ahrens, E.H. RU Professor, 1952 1968-1969; 11 letters (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Includes curriculum vitae and bibliography (1949-1969); support of nomination for 6th award in lipid chemistry (AOCS).
    - American Chemical Society, 1954 1962-1969; 31 letters (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Includes Lecture: 1964 Feb 18 NJ Seton Hall University, North Jersey section ACS lecture series on chemical separations "Countercurrent and dialysis" with program; Lecture: 1967 Feb. Baltimore, Md section ACS meeting "The use of antibiotic polypeptides as models for the study of protein chemistry" with abstract. Also includes reviews of mss for publication in JACS.
    - American Chemical Society 1969 Lecture Tour, 35 letters (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Northwestern lecture tour to local ACS sections, 1969 May (Box 2, Folder 5)
        Correspondence includes biographical sketch; abstracts; arrangements and letters of appreciation. Lectures on "Dialysis" and "Separation based on size and conformation".
        - Salt Lake City, Utah, 1969 May 5
        - Laramie, Wyoming, 1969 May 6
        - Pullman, Washington, 1969 May 7
        - Seattle, Washington, 1969 May 8
        - Corvallis, Oregon, 1969 May 9
    - ACS Award in chromatography and electrophoresis, 1960 January 1-1962 December 31; 20 letters (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Dr. Craig member of award committee. Nominated Stein and Moore (won 1964 award). Includes Stein and Moore biographical material with bibliography.
    - American Society of Biological Chemists (196), 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Includes M.P. Printz nomination for membership. Not listed in bibliography: Gibbons, Sogn, Stern and Craig and Johnson "Natural abundance carbon-13 NMR studies of amino acids and complex peptides" Federation proceedings 29 (1970) 464 abs.
    - Analytical Chemistry, 1952-1971; 11 letters (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Biographical/Historical note
      1968-1970 member of advisory board.
      Includes membership list 1936-1971; agendas and minutes of meetings; also mss reviews and Craig 1952, 1954, 1956 review articles on "Extraction" for; with 1956 biographical note. Also includes Craig book review of H.R.C. Pratt "Countercurrent separation processes", 1967 Elsevier Publishing Co. New York (Not listed in Craig bibliography).
  - B-Bi
    - Bachman, L., 1954 October 26; 1 letter (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Lecture: 1954 Oct 26 Wilmington, Delaware section of ACS analytical group "Title?".
    - Baglioni, C., 1 letter (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Bailey, J.L., 2 letters (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Bailey, S.D., 4 letters (Box 3, Folder 1)
      About Stahl et al ms review.
    - Baldwin, W.H., 2 letters (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Ballhaus, W.F., 2 letters (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Bally, P., 2 letters (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Bangle, R., 2 letters (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Banzer, J.D., 3 letters (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Barany, M., 4 letters (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Baravo, T.C. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Barbato, L., 3 letters (Box 3, Folder 1)